Guide to the Jerry E. and Norma J. Stillwell papers, 1948-1964.
Stillwell, Jerry E. and Norma J. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jerry E. and Norma J. Stillwell papers, 1948-1964.
2621
Stillwell, Jerry E.,
3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, printed material, publications, research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters, diaries, and notes concerning the recording of bird calls, and other ornithology related work.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ornithologists, authors.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters, diaries, and notes concerning the recording of bird calls, begun after Jerry Stillwell's retirement (1948) as a technical editor for the American Petroleum Institute in Dallas, Texas, including extensive correspondence with Peter Paul Kellogg and William Fish, both of the Cornell University Laboratory of Ornithology, which later resulted in their records, "Bird Songs of Door Yard, Field, and Forest" (three albums); manuscripts, typescripts, and correspondence relating to the publication of their articles in NATURE and other naturalists' magazines, and Norma Stillwell's book BIRD SONGS: THE ADVENTURE AND TECHNIQUES IN RECORDING THE SONGS OF AMERICAN BIRDS (Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1964); notebooks (some supplemented by snapshots) and journals of numerous field trips to the Ozarks, Carson National Forest, New Mexico, and other places around the country, particularly in the Midwest and Southwest, which contain observations on birds, trees, and wildflowers; also included are newspaper clippings and other printed material on ornithology and bioacoustics.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Stillwell, Jerry E., -1959.; Fish, William.; Kellogg, Peter Paul, 1899-; Stillwell, Norma J.; Cornell University. Laboratory of Ornithology.
Titles:
Bird songs: the adventure and techniques in recording the songs of the American birds.
Subjects:
Bioacoustics.; Bird-song -- Recording and reproducing.; Birds -- United States.; Ornithology -- United States.; Ornithologists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collection:Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255
Related collection:Peter Paul Kellogg papers, #21-18-893
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Box 1
A-G
H-Q
R-Z
Series II. Birdsong Files: Journals, Manuscripts, and Research
Boxes 2-4
Mainly Norma Stillwell's Files
Mainly Jerry Stillwell's Files
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - A-G
    - American Nature Association, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B-File, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Baird, William and Eloise, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Baumgartner, A. Marguerite, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bedichek, Roy, 1947-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bergstrom, E. Alexander, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Beloit College, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Booth, Ernest, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brasher, Rex, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Burton, L.H., 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - C-File, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Carson, L.B., 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Carter, Mr. and Mrs. J.L., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - CBS (Columbia Broadcasting Company), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cazier, Mont, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chapman, Naomi, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cheatum, Elmer, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Clark, Caroline, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Clemer, J.H., 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Coffey, Ben, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cooper Ornithological Society, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Coronet Instructional Films, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Davie, Paul, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Davis, Irby, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Disney Company (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Dixon, Keith, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Fish, William (1), 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fish, William (2), 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Fristad, Harold, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Gill, C. Terry, 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Glacier Natural History Association, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Goodman, John, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Gordon, Kenneth, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Gunn, William W.H., 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - H-Q
    - Hardwicke, Robert, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Heiser, Joe, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Hines,Paul, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Hostetter, D. Ralph, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Hurlbutt, Catherine, 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Johnson, Clinton, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (1), 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (2), January - July 1951 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (3), August 1951-February 1952 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (4), March - August 1952 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (5), September 1952 - March 1953 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (6), April 1953 - April 1954 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (7), May 1955 - December 1955 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Kellogg, Peter Paul (8), January 1956 - November 1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Kincaid, Edgar, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Lanyon, Wesley, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Lothian, Ivan, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - McAtee, W.L., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - McDougald, Lain, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - McGillivray, Lola and C.M., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - McMurray's Bookshop, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Marsh, Hallan, 1951-1961 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Mason, C. Russell, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Merriam, Mildred and Allen, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Mers, William, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Millard, Glen, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Miller, Loye, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Mills, Pete, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Minnesota, University of, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Montanta State University, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Moore, Nelle (1), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Moore, W.R. (2) (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Moorman, Zella, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Morton, Dur (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Morton, Erle, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Munter, William, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Murray, James, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Oklahoma Ornithological Society, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Parker, H.L., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Parson, Eleanor, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Peggs, Harold, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Peterson, Roger, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Phillips, Neill, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Picasso, Inc., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Pittman, James, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Plumb, Henry, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Quattlebaum, Dr. W. Dave, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - R-Z
    - Randall, G.W., undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Randolph, Vance, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Rapp, William, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Rastall, Mabel, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Rebmann, G. R., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Reid, Bessie, 1937-1983 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Rice, Julian, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Riedel, David, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Rockefeller, Anne (Mrs. Avery), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Rosen, Edith, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Ross, Roland, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Rycraft, Mrs. Thomas, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Sanders, Otty and Ruth, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Saunders, Aretas, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Sclater, Ken, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Shark, Gladys, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Sidders, Ruth, 1959 and undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Sigma Xi, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Skillman, Edward, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Skinner, Mary Lou, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Smiley, Daniel, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Smith, Cecil, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Smith, Frank, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Smith, Turner, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Smithe, Frank, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Spirk, Frank, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Stebbins, Arthur, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 108)
    - Stillman, Nadine, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Stoddard, Herbert, 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 110)
    - Story, Mrs. Joseph, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Sturmer, Mary, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Sutton, George Miksch, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Taber, Wendell, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Tall, Joel, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - Tanghe, Leo, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 116)
    - Taylor, Robert, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - Taylor, Mary and Walter, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - Terry, Spencer, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - Thies, Ernestine, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 120)
    - Thomas, Ruth, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 121)
    - Torrey, Paul, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 122)
    - Torti, Mrs. M.L., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Treat, Dorthy, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Tulsa Audubon Society, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 125)
    - Turner, Carrol, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 126)
    - Tulser, F.A., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 127)
    - Wagner, Sterling and Alice, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 128)
    - Walker, Lewis Wayne, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 129)
    - Wallenberg, Venice, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - Watson, Margaret, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 131)
    - Watson, B.B. and Martha (Box 1, Folder 132)
    - Weiss, Stanley, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 133)
    - Weston, Dr. Henry Jr. (Box 1, Folder 134)
    - Whitaker, Lovie, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 135)
    - Wilkinson Brothers Co. (Box 1, Folder 136)
    - Williams, Laidlaw, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 137)
    - Williams, Mrs. S.R., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 138)
    - Wilson, Belle, 1954, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 139)
    - Wilson Ornithological Club, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 140)
    - Winford, Edith, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 141)
    - Wing, Anne and Leonard (Box 1, Folder 142)
    - Wisconsin, University of, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 143)
    - Wood, Merrill, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 144)
    - Wrather, W.E., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 145)
    - WFAA (Dallas), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 146)
- Series II. Birdsong Files: Journals, Manuscripts and Research
  - Mainly Norma Stillwell's Files
    - Journal (November 22, 1948-November 19, 1953), 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Journal (November 22, 1953 - January 1, 1957), 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Journal (January 2, 1957- June 23, 1959), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Recorders Notebook, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Notebooks, 1956-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Notebook of birds recorded and 1 typewritten with notes on identification by bird types
    - Kingbird, Couch's, 1952-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes notes on birdsong written in musical notation
    - Owl, Ferruginous Pigmy, 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Prairie Chicken, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Solitaire Townsend's, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Avian Echoes from the Southwest, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      For Texas Ornithological Society
    - "Rambles of a Pair of Bird Recorders", 1956-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Chapter 1 "Reel Beginnings"
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Chapter 2 "The Valley" and Chapter 3 "Few Birds, But Friendly Folks"
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Chapter 4 "Kelloggs and the Everglades" and two discarded sections
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version 4, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Chapter 5 "Otter Creek Park", Chapter 6 "Avian Echoes" and 1 discarded section
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version 5, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Chapter 7 "Year of the Hermit Thrush", Chapter 8 "We Go West", Cahpter 9 "Singing Stars and Snowy Vistas" last page corresponds to last page of Chapter 10 "The Birds Give an Encore"
    - Birdsong Adventures - Early Version, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Chapter 10 "The Birds Give an Encore" and miscellaneous draft chapters
    - "Birdsong Adventures" Draft - Pages 1-87 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Birdsong Adventures" Draft - Pages 107-236 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Birdsong Adventures" Printer's Copy 1, c. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Birdsong Adventures - Printer's Copy 2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Chapter 2 "The Valley", Chapter 3 "Few Birds, But Friendly Folks" and Chapter 4 "Kelloggs and the Everglades"
    - "Birdsong Adventures" Printer's Copy 3, c. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Chapter 5 "Otter Creek Park", Chapter 6 "Avian Echoes" and Chapter 7 "Year of the Hermit Thrush"
    - "Birdsong Adventures" Printer's Copy 4, c. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Chapter 8 "We Go West", Cahpter 9 "Singing Stars and Snowy Vistas", Chapter 10 "The Birds Give an Encore" and Index
    - Bio-Acoustics Newsletter, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1950-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, Christmas letters and sales material (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bird Songs: Adventures and Techniques in Recording the Songs of American Birds, 1964 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Mainly Jerry Stillwell's Files
    - Annual Vacation: Tres Ritos and Red River, New Mexico, 1931 (Box 2, Volume 2)
      In a 3 ring notebook marked "Erie Days". Contains photographs.
    - Rapidity of Bird Calls, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Memo Notes of Jerry Stillwell, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      biographical writings with photographs
    - Correspondence with Rex Brasher, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Key and Guide to the Woody Plants of Dallas County by Norma Stillwell, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - A Motor Boat Trip on the Neosho River, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - American Ornithologists' Union related (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Articles and Notes on Grasses, 1928-1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Manuscripts, 1949-1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Attractions for the Birds by Norma and Jerry Stillwell, c. 1934 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Manuscripts, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - The Roadrunner, c. 1935 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Preferential Complex, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Crows, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - The Scissor-tailed Flycatcher, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Vagabond Trails" and "New Trails and Old" (1), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "New Trails and Old" (2), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Tres Ritos, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Publications (1), 1954-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      articles and clippings
    - Publications (2), 1935-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Publications (3), 1930-1935, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Woodland Notes, 1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Book 6: Journal, January 8, 1933-April 23, 1933, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Book 1, Number7: August 23, 1931, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Book 1, Number 6: August 16, 1931, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hermit Thrushes, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - American Petroleum Institute - Miscellaneous, 1926-1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Includes photos and correspondence
    - Brush Recorder, 1959-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - A Narrative of Exploration and Adventure in the Rocky Mountains (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Radio Programs, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Our Studies of Bird Song", 1951-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Song Patterns, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bird Song Studies, 1953-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bird Song Studies (2), 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Wilson's Bulletin
    - Bird Song Studies (3), 1935-1950[1952] (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Articles and reprints